<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A notable sermon made within S. Paules church in Lo[n]don in the presence of certen of the kinges and Quenes moost honorable priuie cou[n]sell at the celebration of the exequies of the right excellent and famous princesse, lady Ione, Quene of Spayne, Sicilie [and] Nauarre. [et]c. the xviij. of Iune, Anno. 1555. By maister Iohn Feckenam, deane of the sayd churche of Paules. Set furth at the request of some in auctoritie whose request could not be denayed.</title>
            <author>Feckenham, John de, 1518?-1585.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10744</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847697</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00609)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 223:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A notable sermon made within S. Paules church in Lo[n]don in the presence of certen of the kinges and Quenes moost honorable priuie cou[n]sell at the celebration of the exequies of the right excellent and famous princesse, lady Ione, Quene of Spayne, Sicilie [and] Nauarre. [et]c. the xviij. of Iune, Anno. 1555. By maister Iohn Feckenam, deane of the sayd churche of Paules. Set furth at the request of some in auctoritie whose request could not be denayed.</title>
                  <author>Feckenham, John de, 1518?-1585.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Roberti Caly, typographi,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Mense Augusti. Anno. 1555. Cum priuilegio.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jeanne --  II, --  Queen of Navarre, 1311-1349 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12753:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12753:2"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12753:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> A notable ſermon made within S. Paules church in Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, in the preſence of certen of the kinges and Quenes mooſt honorable priuie cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell at the celebration of the exequies of the right ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and famous Princeſſe, lady Ione, Quene of Spayne, Sicilie &amp; Nauarre, &amp;c. the xviij. of Iune. <hi rend="italic">Anno.</hi> 1555. By maiſter Iohn Feckenam, Deane of the ſayd Churche of Paules.</p>
            <p>¶ Set furth at the requeſt of ſome in auctoritie whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt could not be denayed.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi rend="italic">EXCVSVM LONDINI IN aedibus Roberti Caly, Typographi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Menſe Augusti. Anno. 1555. Cum priuilegio.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12753:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12753:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi rend="roman">Gens abſque conſilio, &amp; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Theme. <bibl>Deut. xxxij.</bibl>
                  </note> 
                  <hi rend="roman">prudentia: Vtinam ſaperent, &amp; intelligerent, ac nouiſſima pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiderent.</hi> People voyde of good counſel, voide of wiſedom, and of all foreſyghte of thynges to come. <hi rend="roman">Vtinam ſaperent et intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent:</hi> Would God they would be wiſe and vnderſtande, and prouide for the laſt thinges.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are the</hi> wordes of the prophet Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, written in the xxxii. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre of Deute. Which I haue choſen as a theme or propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at this tyme to ſtaye vpon, for ſo muche as you do ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtlye declare your ſelues to be <hi rend="roman">gens abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio,</hi> People
<pb facs="tcp:12753:4"/> cleane voide of all good conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, knowledge or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell what to do: <hi rend="roman">&amp; ſine prudentia,</hi> &amp; wythout wyſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; foreſighte to knowe howe thinges ought to be done. That by the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration made of the ſaid theme, you myghte be broughte into ſome more better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of your ſelues &amp; of your owne moſt fraile and brickel eſtates: and thereby to learne nowe at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth (after ſo oft callinges vpon, &amp; ſo many vertuous and moſt godlye inſtructions) theſe thre notable and chiefe ſeſſons: wherof the firſt is <hi rend="roman">ſapere,</hi> to be <note place="margin">iij, Leſſons.</note> wiſe: the ſeconde is <hi rend="roman">intelligere,</hi> to vnderſtande: and the thirde is <hi rend="roman">nouiſſima prouidere,</hi> to make prouiſion for the laſte thinges. That by the fyrſt leſſon &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of wiſedome, we maye haue ſure knowledge of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:12753:4"/> paſt. By our ſeconde leſſon of perfite vnderſtandinge, we may haue the right conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thinges preſent: therby the more earneſtly to atteyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges to come: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. xiiij. of the prouerbes: <hi rend="roman">acceptus eſt regi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prou. xiiij.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">intelligens.</hi> A wiſe ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaith he, whiche by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thinges paſt, and wiſe diſpoſition of thinges preſent, ſhall here in his lyfe time make good prouiſion for thinges to come: <hi rend="roman">acceptus eſt regi,</hi> is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and accepted before God. Let vs therfore at this preſent learne of the prophet Moyſes theſe thre notable leſſons, that is to ſay, <hi rend="roman">ſapere, intelligere, ac no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſſima prouidere,</hi> to be wyſe, to vnderſtand, and to prouide for
<pb facs="tcp:12753:5"/> the laſt thinges, that we maye be made wiſe ſeruauntes and prudent miniſters, &amp; be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and approued before God oure Lorde and kynge. When by the firſt leſſon <hi rend="roman">(ſapere)</hi> of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, we may here in this lyfe haue intelligence of al thinges apperteyning to God: By oure ſeconde leſſon <hi rend="roman">(intelligere)</hi> of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete and perfit vnderſtanding howe paſſing and tranſitorye, howe vayne and ſlydyng theſe worldly thinges are: Whereby we ſhal the more eaſely atteine the thirde leſſon <hi rend="roman">(nouiſſima pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidere)</hi> of good prouiſion ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge for the laſte thinges and thinges to come. When by the firſt leſſon of a wyſe &amp; circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte knowledge, a man ſhall perceyue Gods moſt vprighte &amp; terrible iudgementes, which
<pb facs="tcp:12753:5"/> can not be deceyued: By the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde leſſon of cleare vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding. he ſhall enter into the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of him ſelfe, of his owne corruption and mortall nature, which can not be auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Therby to make the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prouiſion for the ioyes to come, which can not be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Be you wiſe therfore (dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued) &amp; let vs from hence furth be no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger <hi rend="roman">ſicut ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio &amp; ſine prudentia,</hi> as people voyde of good counſell, and withoute wiſedome and knowledge: but let vs now pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſently lift vp our hartes. &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare oure ſelues to learne theſe thre ſo profitable leſſons, <hi rend="roman">ſape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, intelligere, ac nouiſſima proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere,</hi> to be wiſe, to vnderſtande and to prouide for the laſt thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: and with ſo much the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:12753:6"/> willes, for that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed almightie God <hi rend="roman">(Qui non</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezec, xviij.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">vult mortem peccatoris ſed, magis vt conuertatur et viuat</hi> who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhould turne from his wickednes and liue) like a moſt bountiful and moſt mercyfull father to ſende hys prophet Moiſes as an ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadoure to excite &amp; admoniſhe, and call vpon vs for the ſame with theſe wordes whiche I haue choſen for my theme. <hi rend="roman">Gens abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio &amp; ſine prudentia, Vtinam ſaperent &amp; intelligerent ac nouiſſima prouidere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> People voide of good counſell, voide of wiſedome and all foreſyght of thinges to come. Woulde God they wold be wiſe, &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; prouide for the laſte thinges.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Hic fiunt preces.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12753:6"/>
            <p> 
               <hi rend="roman">Gens abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio &amp; ſine pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Thema. i. &amp;. ii. mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brum.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">vtinam ſaperent, &amp; intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, ac nouiſſima prouiderent.</hi> People voide of good counſell voide of wiſedome, and of all foreſight of thinges to come, <hi rend="roman">v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinam ſaperent &amp; intelligerent:</hi> Would god they wold be wiſe, and vnderſtande, and prouide for the laſt thinges.</p>
            <p>Firſt the prophete Moyſes <note place="margin">Firſte to knowe that this preſent lyfe is ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge.</note> Gods ambaſſadour, earneſtly wiſheth and deſireth that we mortall creatures here liuinge in this worlde; as it were in a ſlipper paſſage vnto deth, ſhold be of ſuche ripe wiſedome and perfite vnderſtandinge, as to knowe howe that this preſent life is but tranſitory, and (as Iob ſaith) <hi rend="roman">ꝙ quaſi flos egreditur</hi> that it paſſeth away as it were <note place="margin">Iob. xiiij.</note> a floure, <hi rend="roman">fugit velut vmbra,</hi> fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:12753:7"/> as it were a ſhadowe. <hi rend="roman">&amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletur multis miſeriis,</hi> and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bewrapped in wretchednes, ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iecte to all maner of vanitie, defoiled with the filthineſſe of ſinne, and that it ſhall periſhe within a ſhorte time. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ſcriptures the life of man is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared and reſembled vnto thinges of moſte vanitie: As ſomtime to herbes or graſſe growing in the feld, as the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet Dauid ſaith. <hi rend="roman">Homo ſicut</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. cii.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">foenum dies eius, ſicut flos agri ſic efflorebit.</hi> The daies of man are but as graſſe, he doeth flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe for a litle ſeaſon euen as it were a flowre in the felde. Somtime to a ſhadow and va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie. <hi rend="roman">Homo vanitati ſimilis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. cxliii.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">eſt, dies eius ſicut vmbra prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tereunt,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt. Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made like vnto a vanitie, his
<pb facs="tcp:12753:7"/> daies paſſe awaye as it were a ſhadowe. Somtime to a wind. <hi rend="roman">Ventus enim eſt vita mea,</hi> ſaieth Iob. My life is but a blaſte of <note place="margin">Iob. vij.</note> winde: Somtime to a vapor, as Sainct Iames ſaieth. <hi rend="roman">Quae eſt eni vita veſtra? vapor eſt ad mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iaco. iiii.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">parens, &amp; deinceps exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minabitur.</hi> What thing is your life, ſaith ſainte Iames? It is, ſaieth he, euen a vapor appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for a litle ſeaſon, and then it vaniſheth awaye: And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. <hi rend="roman">Nihil enim ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es mei,</hi> ſaith Iob. For my daies <note place="margin">Iob. vii.</note> are nothing: God ſo diſpoſinge cleane to withdraw the inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate loue of this wretched lyfe out of the hartes of men. When there is no man of any wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or vnderſtanding that ſhoulde much regard or ſet by that life whiche is ſo vncertaine as the
<pb facs="tcp:12753:8"/> floure of the felde, ſo inconſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as the winde, ſo vaine as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, ſo tranſitory as a vapor toſſed and tombled in the aire, and finally ſo litle worth as no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing: But by this wiſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtandynge, the more vile that this preſent life is knowen to be, the more eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye it maye of all men be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, deſpiſed &amp; ſet at nought for the loue of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> life, which ſhal neuer vaniſh, but euer endure.</p>
            <p>Beſides this knowledge, how fikell, howe fraile, howe vayne <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. To know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he miſeries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herof.</note> and howe tranſitory this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life is, the prophete Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes wiſheth vnto vs a further knowledge to be had of thys our mortall lyfe, and that we mortall creatures woulde be wiſe and vnderſtande, how ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull is the firſt entringe of
<pb facs="tcp:12753:8"/> mans lyfe into this wretched <note place="margin">The firſt entry of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into this world is ful of ſorowe.</note> worlde, <hi rend="roman">maximo cum fletu, vagi tu, inertia &amp; imbecillitate mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> with much wepynge &amp; cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with muche ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and feblenes: He is borne naked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worlde and naked from hence he muſte departe againe, made of the earth, and to the earth he muſt retourne agayn. How chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable his life is for his time here abydinge, and as <note place="margin">The tyme of his aby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding here is ful of muta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilitie. <hi rend="roman">Iob. xiiij</hi>
               </note> Iob ſaieth. <hi rend="roman">Nunquam in eodem ſtatu permanens.</hi> Neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in one ſtate, now riche nowe poore nowe hoole nowe ſicke, nowe merye nowe ſorye, nowe counynge nowe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, nowe ſeyng nowe blind, nowe free nowe bonde, nowe good nowe euyll, And finallye <note place="margin">His ende departure full of fear</note> howe terrible and fearfull ſhal be the paſſynge of the ſame at
<pb facs="tcp:12753:9"/> his departure againe.</p>
            <p>Ouer and beſide theſe know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledges, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. To know the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of death.</note> the prophete Moyſes earneſtly wiſheth that we mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable creatures here abiding in this worlde, woulde once be wiſe and vnderſtande and knowe the great neceſſitie of death that raigneth ouer vs: An acte and decree beinge al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie paſt againſt vs, that die we muſt. <hi rend="roman">Statutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt</hi> (ſaieth S. <note place="margin">Hebre. ix.</note> Paule) <hi rend="roman">o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nibꝰ hominibus femel mori.</hi> It is decreed &amp; appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for al men once to die. And this great ſtraite &amp; neceſſitie of death then fyrſt beginneth to take place in man, when the ſoule is ioyned to the bodie, and continueth in man vntyll the ſeparation of the ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodie againe. For life is no ſoner comme into the bodie by
<pb facs="tcp:12753:9"/> the preſence of the ſoule, but but death furthwithall iſſueth out of his graue and ſepulchre to take away the ſame againe: and by the very ſame way that life goeth, death commeth. Do not we ſee the order of this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent life to be ſuche, that after infancie commeth childhod, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter childhod youth, after youth mans ſtate, after mans ſtate age, then olde age, and ſo at the laſt death? The whiche or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and naturall courſe can by no law, ſtatute or meanes that man can inuent, be infringed or broken, neither yet once ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or pluckt backe. No not Mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nos <note place="margin">Minos. Lycurgus.</note> the lawe maker at Crete, nor Lycurgus at Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, nor yet the wife Solon in <note place="margin">Solon.</note> his lawes deuiſed at Athenes, could make any repeale of this
<pb facs="tcp:12753:10"/> decree and ordinaunce of God. When from the firſt man Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto this moſt noble and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious queene of Spaine late departed, none hath eſcaped or ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſcape this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death. No not Noe for all his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, <note place="margin">Noe. Loth.</note> nor Loth for al his hoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pitalitie, nor yet Toby for all his dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in buriyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead <note place="margin">Toby.</note> could eſcape this rigorous ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſtrong &amp; mightie faith of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor the ſupplanting <note place="margin">Abraham.</note> of vices that was in Iacob, nor the great mekenes of the <note place="margin">Iacob.</note> prophete Moyſes, nor the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie of Ioſeph, nor yet the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines <note place="margin">Moyſes. Ioſeph.</note> of the prophet Samuel, that coulde perſuade death to be the more fauourable to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The great wiſedome, riches, might &amp; power, of kyng Salo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon, <note place="margin">Salomon.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12753:10"/> the great ſtrength &amp; force of Sampſon agaynſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the puiſſaunce of the king and prophete Dauid, his fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of chiualtie &amp; great mighte in armes coulde not auaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the aſſaultes of deathe: death beynge fauourable to no man, but like cruell and tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous to euery man. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do rede that death was portred &amp; painted of the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims with the face and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of a tiraunt hauinge in his hande redie bente bow and arrowes to kill, ſlea, and ſhote at euerye man withoute all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte or acception of perſons. And in daily louſing of his dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes at vs, albeit that ſometime he ouerſhoteth vs, and in fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge of vs ſleath kinges. Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Dukes, Earles, Lordes:
<pb facs="tcp:12753:11"/> Sometime his darte lighteth to ſhorte of vs, and in the ſtead of vs, ſtriketh our ſeruauntes, oure tenauntes and our poore innocent neighbours dwelling by vs, ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>time his dart maketh a very narrow myſſe of vs on the right hand, and killeth our wiues, our children, oure fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; kynſfolkes ſo derely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued. And albeit that his fierce dart glyde ſomtymes to wyde on the lefte hande, and in fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of vs, kylleth oure aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries and enemies, and therby bryngeth vs oftymes into a vaine comforte, fooliſhe mirth and reioyſinge, makinge vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that he is our frende in the diſpatche of thoſe that loue vs not: Yet the tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie of his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de is ſuche that he will not faile at the length to hitte vs. And
<pb facs="tcp:12753:11"/> wheras death at the beginning was ſo vnripe and vnperfite a boweman, that he firſte ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge and louſynge his dartes at oure firſt father Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it was nine hundred and thirtie yeres, <note place="margin">Adam, 930.</note> (whoſe age was no fewer yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre) before he coulde ſtrik him. And wheras he bare his bow dailie bent againſt his ſonne Seth, it was nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <note place="margin">Seth. 912.</note> and twelue yeares, before he coulde hit him. And wheras he daylye laie in waite to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe with his dart Mathu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <note place="margin">Mathuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. 969.</note> Enoches ſonne, it was nine hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred threſcore and nine yeares before he coulde ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw him. Yet within a certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpace after, by daily cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e and exerciſe of his hande, he began to waxe a more perfitte bowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manne, euerye daye ſhootynge
<pb facs="tcp:12753:12"/> more nere his marke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other, in ſo muche that by the time &amp; dayes of kynge Dauid, he got him ſuche a redineſſe and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe of ſhotynge, that he would not haue failed (for the more part) to ſtrike his marke within the ſpace of. lxx. or. lxxx. yeres, like as the prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid witneſſeth ſaying. <hi rend="roman">Dies an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 89.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">noſtroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ipſis ſeptua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta annis. Si autem in pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus octoginta anni, &amp; amplius eorum labor &amp; dolor.</hi> The daies of our age<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaith he, are. lxx. ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and yf men be ſo ſtronge that they come to. lxxx. what ſo euer is more, is nothinge but labour and ſorowe.</p>
            <p>Thus you may perceiue not <note place="margin">The tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of death</note> only the neceſſitie of deth, that die we muſt: but alſo how cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell a tiraunte deathe is, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:12753:12"/> tyrannye daylye increaſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte vs more and more, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye day ſhorteninge oure liues and ſhootynge more nere the marke then other. Whoſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes and lieng in wayte for vs be wonderfull ſubtile and craftie. Sometime he maketh towarde vs as it were with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen batayle, ſendynge before hym vnto vs diuerſe infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſyckneſſes: and vnto, ſome hoare heares, blered eies, tremblinge and ſhakinge han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ſtouping ſhulders and cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked backes, as it were meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or herauldes at armes ſent before him. Somtime he commeth priuely creapinge as a thefe, and ſtealynge vpon vs like as he dyd vpon the riche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of whome we rede in the twelfeth of ſaincte Lukes goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,
<pb facs="tcp:12753:13"/> ſending to'vs no warnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or meſſengers at all before him. Therfore almightie God, to cauſe vs to be in a redines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte his ſodaine comminge, and oftentimes to haue the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine houre of deathe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce (whiche our fraile and deadlie ſicknes maketh vs ſo ofte to forget) hath ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs his Prophete Moyſes: which prophete Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes much lamentyng and ſorowynge our great blindnes, ſaieth vnto vs theſe wordes of my Theme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Gens abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio, &amp; ſine pru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dentia: Vtinam ſaperent et intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, ac nouiſſima.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But why doeth the Prophet Moyſes ſo vehementlye wiſhe and deſire vnto vs this cleare wiſedome, and perfite vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge of the vanitie of this
<pb facs="tcp:12753:13"/> preſente lyfe, of the myſerye of the ſame, of the filthines of our owne corruption, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of deathe? Doubtleſſe forbycauſe the perfite know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and throughe vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of theſe thynges are in vs, the deſtruction of pride, the quenchinge of enuie, the verye medicine of malice, the driuing awaye of lecherye, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of all worldly boaſt &amp; vanitie, and finallye the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueringe of euerlaſtynge lyfe. For what thinge (I praye you) lyeth in the compaſſe of mans wit, that ſooner moueth a man to mekenes, &amp; to the perfection of al holines, then doth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his own corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and the diligent vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge how that he liueth here in this wretched world as an outlaw
<pb facs="tcp:12753:14"/> a pilgrime, a geſte full poore in all vertues, full vnſtable in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, peraduenture not aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge here till to morowe? For this maner of conſideration &amp; diligent vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſhall cauſe a man to deſpiſe al the boaſte of this life, the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines of worldly vanities, and all vncleane luſtes and delecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions of the fleſhe. And in this maner of thinkinge, the ſoule receiueth knowledge of ſinne, the knowledge of ſynne bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth repentaunce, repentaunce cauſeth amendemente and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction makynge for ſynne, and all theſe together do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender in a man a verye hope, ſure truſte, and firme ſtrength in our Lorde God. The which thinge the Prophete Moyſes throughlye conſideringe, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth
<pb facs="tcp:12753:14"/> by feruent deſire, ſayinge vnto you the wordes of my Theme. <hi rend="roman">Vtinam ſaperent &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligerent ac nouiſſima prouide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi> Would God men woulde be wiſe and vnderſtande, and prouide for the laſt thinges.</p>
            <p>But alas howe longe ſhall we be <hi rend="roman">ſicut gens abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio &amp; ſine prudentia,</hi> as it were peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple voide of good counſell and without foreſight and wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? All to fewe beynge amonge vs that haue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration, the wyſedome and cleare vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge of theſe thynges in perfit remembraunce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ful few there be that ſette before their eyes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of their own infirmitie, their bodely corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the minde of their ſinnes, the day of their deth, or yet the paynes of hell: but muche like
<pb facs="tcp:12753:15"/> vnto brute beaſtes do pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cede liuinge here in this world, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regardynge God, nor yet verye muche fearing the deuil. Woulde God therfore, in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyngs thys exhortation of the prophet Moyſes, we would once begin to waxe wiſe, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande, and to make proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the laſte thinges: And <note place="margin">The glaſſe of our own corruption.</note> that by the contemplation and beholdinge of our ſelues in this ſo profytable a myrroure and glaſſe of our owne corruption, and frayle nature, and of the greate certitude of death that abydeth therin. At whoſe firſt entrye and breakynge into our houſes, beholde howe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience begynneth to dreade, howe the hearte quaketh, the heade ſtoupeth, the witte wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth,
<pb facs="tcp:12753:15"/> the ſtrengthe faileth, the viſage waxeth pale, the tonge fombleth, the breath goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, the ſpeche very rare and thynne, all the beautie of the body cleane tourned into a gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelye and fylthye corruption: and after that the bodye is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, it falleth into a carionlyke ſtenche, the fleſhe cleane tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into grubbes meate. Be you wyſe therefore, O ye mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall creatures, and vnderſtand howe that thys is an horryble ſyghte, but it is full profitable.</p>
            <p>O howe bleſſed and happye is he, that circumſpectlye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth hym ſelfe in this mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or glaſſe, when there is no crafte, no medicine, none inſtruction or teachynge that ſooner deſtroyeth all
<pb facs="tcp:12753:16"/> vices, and planteth al vertues, then doeth the inwarde behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of a mans owne corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and laſte ende.</p>
            <p>To this glaſſe therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire <note place="margin">Yonge men</note> ye firſt, O ye luſtie yonge men, (whiche by the deceitfull wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of your youth do go ſo vpright, ſtretching out your ſelues, bearing vp your heades aloft with luſtie courage) and learne of ſtronge Sampſon, of mightie Golias, and of the har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die captaine Holofernes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which periſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boaſte of their owne ſtrength, what great folie it is to glorie in the ſtrength of the bodye, whiche ſhall ſo ſene decay and be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen.</p>
            <p>To this glaſſe come ye al, O <note place="margin">Olde men.</note> ye olde fathers, vnto whome deathe beyng very fauourable
<pb facs="tcp:12753:16"/> hath ſent before him vnto you ſo many meſſengers, as youre hoare hears, bleared eies, drop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pinge noſes, ſagginge chekes, your lippes hanging, ſtowping neckes and ſhulders: come you hither and beholde your ſelues and learne at the leaſt wayes nowe in youre olde age to be wiſe &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de what vaine hope you be in, whiche do loke and make your moſt vayne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptes, to liue one yeare lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: be ye neuer of ſo greate an age, euer crepynge awaie and fore fearinge to die. O ye olde fathers and hoare heares, why feare ye to die at. lxx. or lxxx. ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of age, when all the tyme that ye ſhal liue after is in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, in greuous aches, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual decaiyng, and neuer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, but rolinge, relinge and
<pb facs="tcp:12753:17"/> redye to fall in to the graue, whiche you do ſo lothe? Why therfore feare ye ſo ſore to dye, when by deathe God doethe chaunge vs from an olde filthy houſe into a newe? For certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie death is but a playe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the player (if he be wiſe) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentureth but a litle to winne muche. Whiche thynge is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye eaſlie perceyued of all thoſe men which are of perfit know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, howe muche bleſſednes God is of, vnto whome we hope to go by death, and of how muche euyll theſe worldly men are, wyth whome we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant here by life.</p>
            <p>O ye gentlemen and men of <note place="margin">Gentlemen</note> nobilitie, come you hyther alſo to beholde your ſelues in thys glaſſe. And here you ſhal learne to be wiſe &amp; vnderſtande, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:12753:17"/> the filthie grubbe worme or maggotte dare not aſwell breede in youre, fleſhe of your bloode whereof you bragge ſo muche, &amp; waſt &amp; conſume your carcaſſes, of your partes alwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes ſo deintely made of &amp; ſo de licately nouriſhed &amp; fed, aſwell as other inferior &amp; porer mens.</p>
            <p>O ye gentlewomen &amp; faire <note place="margin">Gentle wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men.</note> ladies greatlie deliting in pure glaſſes, forgette not I praye you to beholde youre ſelues in this glaſſe of al other moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, which are ſo fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen here in this worlde to ſet forth youre ſelues, wyth youre browdred heare (whiche is a greate abuſe) youre fyngers be ſet with ringes, bearing purſes full of ſwete ſauoures &amp; ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and bandes aboute youre neckes fynely wroughte wyth
<pb facs="tcp:12753:18"/> ſilke, and beſet with pearles, with bracelets ful of gaudies, and ſuche other like maner of diſguiſinges. O ye foliſhe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men whiche do beſtowe and ſpende a greate parte of youre liues in the deuiſe of ſuche va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. <hi rend="roman">Vtinam ſaperetis &amp; intelli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geretis.</hi> Would God you would once lerne to be wiſe, perceiue &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with what good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye trinkettes you ſhall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parailled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtraitnes of your graues and ſepulchers, where ye ſhall with Iob ſay. <hi rend="roman">Putredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni dixi, pater meus es tu mater mea</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob. xvij.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">&amp; ſoror mea vermibus.</hi> I ſaide vnto corruption, thou arte my father: and vnto the wormes you are my mother and my ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Why do ye therfore make ſo much of ſo filthie a carkas, and waſt ſo much time in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhinge,
<pb facs="tcp:12753:18"/> kemming and pranking of the ſame, vnto no ſmale prid and oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation: when ye do but looſe youre laboures, and in ſo doynge you do nothing els, but floure a fylthye donghyll, and garniſh a ſmokie miſkin, which you ſhall neuer make ſauerie, waſhe him neuer ſo muche.</p>
            <p>O ye great richmen, men of <note place="margin">Riche and honourable men.</note> authoritie, honour and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whiche are as Gods here in this world, all thinges ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in beinge at your commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by reaſon of your autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and riches, Come you alſo and repaire vnto this glaſſe, &amp; tell me whether you can wyth all your authoritie, might and power, with all your golde ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and worldlie treaſures, either feare or corrupte death, yea ſo much as to make him ſo
<pb facs="tcp:12753:19"/> partial and fauourable to you, that he will let you eſcape: like as in al other worldly thinges els, you can do, peruertinge all good lawes by the ſuppreſſion of iuſtice. O ye worldlynges which liue here as goddes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth: Do not you here ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge perceiue, howe the time flieth without retorninge? how the life traueileth on her iorney withoute ceaſſynge? howe the fleſhe conſumeth withoute fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge? and howe the glorye of this woride paſſeth as it neuer had bene? (The landes, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, riches, iewelles and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures therof oftentimes falling into thoſe mennes handes, who by oure willes ſhoulde haue the leſt part therof.) Why therfore be ye ſo forgetfull of youre ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and ſo noſelde in all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:12753:19"/> vanityes, as thoughe they ſhoulde euer contynewe and neuer take ende.</p>
            <p>O ye kynges and Princes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye <note place="margin">Kinges Princes.</note> magiſtrates and rulers of thys world. O ye prelates &amp; byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, hauynge charge of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes <note place="margin">Prieſtes, Byſhippes &amp; ſubiectes</note> churche and familie. O all ye of hyghe and lowe degree, whether ye be gouernoures or ſubiectes, maiſters or ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſuperiours or inferiours, come hither &amp; beholde your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in this cleare mirroure and glaſſe of your own corruption: &amp; by a diligent examinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and conſideration wyth youre ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues <note place="margin">Conſider what we were.</note> what you haue bene, and of howe vyle a matter borne in to thys worlde <hi rend="roman">(ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe ex men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruo mulieris:)</hi> What you are at thys preſente touchynge the <note place="margin">What we are.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12753:20"/> bodie, when as S. Bernard ſaith. <hi rend="roman">Conſidera quid per oculos, quid per nares, per os, per aures, coeteros<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> corporis meatus emiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, et nun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> vidi vilius ſterquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider wel, ſaith he, what a man ſendeth furth and auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by his eies, his noſetrilles, his mouth, his eares, and other the paſſages and pooers of the bodie, and thou maieſt well ſay <hi rend="roman">nun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> vidi vilius ſterquilinium.</hi> I neuer ſaw a viler donghil: And what we ſhall be, <hi rend="roman">nempe terra et</hi> 
               <note place="margin">What we ſhall be.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">ciuis.</hi> Euen verie earth and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes. <hi rend="roman">Quia pulnis es &amp; in puluere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuerteris.</hi> For duſte thou arte, &amp; <note place="margin">Geneſ. iij.</note> into duſt thou ſhalt returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and you ſhall beginne to waxe wiſe, perceaue and vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande, howe muche more mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we haue in our ſelues of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie then of pryde, of meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:12753:20"/> then of oſtentation, of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe then of ioye, howe muche more matter alſo of abhorring oure ſelues, then of gloriynge in oure ſelues, of contemnynge &amp; ſetting this world at nought then of reioyſe in the worlde, &amp; of followynge the moſte godlie and holſome counſel of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Moyſes, then of neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng the ſame. Which prophete as an embaſſador ſente of God to plucke vs into a more perfite remembraunce and knowledge of our ſelues with moſt earneſt and heartie deſire wiſheth the ſame, ſaying vnto vs the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of my theme. <hi rend="roman">vtinam ſape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent et intelligerent.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And this wiſedome and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding beyng firſt obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and got by the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diligent beholdynge of
<pb facs="tcp:12753:21"/> our ſelues in this mirrour and glaſſe of our own corruption &amp; mortal nature: let vs now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt part of this theme, &amp; expreſſe in a worde or. ij. what <note place="margin">To prouide for the laſte thynges.</note> prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſte be made of oure partes for the laſt thynges, &amp; ſo I ſhall ſhortly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit you to go. And touchig a right order to be obſerued in this prouiſion ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for the laſt thinges: Firſte I ſhall declare vnto you, what theſe laſt thinges are, &amp; ſo after what prouiſion of oure partes oughte to be made for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And theſe laſt thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges being many in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges may iuſtly be called <hi rend="roman">nouiſſima,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte thinges which ſhall ſerue at the laſt, &amp; be of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to the ſoule of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when al frendſhip, al helpe, confort &amp; pleaſure of this world ſhal faile.) But here at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb facs="tcp:12753:21"/> to vſe breuitie, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate chefely of theſe foure laſt <note place="margin">Foure laſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thynges.</note> thinges, that is to ſay, of death, of the iudgement of God, of the paynes of hell, and of the ioyes of heauen. For the which foure laſt thinges I would haue you in the ſhort courſe of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t life to make prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Firſt that <note place="margin">Firſt.</note> we may here finiſh our life, and die wel. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that we ma re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <note place="margin">Seconde.</note> at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of God a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable &amp; a merciful iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Thirdly, we muſt here prouide <note place="margin">Thyrde.</note> to auoide the horrible paines of hel. Fourth &amp; laſt we muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouide <note place="margin">Fourthe.</note> ſo here to liue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be partakers of the life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting &amp; ioyes of heauen. And to auoide co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> herin, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of this our prouiſon making muſt be ſundry &amp; diuerſe, like as the vocations degrees, and eſtates
<pb facs="tcp:12753:22"/> of men be ſundry and diuerſe. As the Biſhoppes, Prieſtes &amp; prelates of chriſtes churche ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the flocke of Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted to their great cure and charge. They muſt make their prouiſion for theſe foure laſte thinges by a circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpect fedinge of Chriſtes flock with good and holſome doctrine, by a diligent ſerche of their partes to be made for the loſte ſhepe whiche haue periſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> late plague of errours and Hereſies: by a wiſe bringing of them backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the folde and vnitie of Chriſtes church, by a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful binding and knitting of the woundes of the ſoore cut and mangled ſhepe: by a charitable nouriſhinge and confortinge of the weake, ſicke &amp; feble among them, hauynge in their breſtes
<pb facs="tcp:12753:22"/> towarde their flockes the very zeale of a good paſtour and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perde: whoſe zeale is ſuche (as Chriſt witneſſeth) <hi rend="roman">ꝙ anima ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>det pro ouibus ſuis,</hi> that he will <note place="margin">Iohn. x.</note> not ſticke to giue his life for his ſhepe, like as our ſauiour chriſt hath geuen vs example alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and as Moyſes deſired <hi rend="roman">de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leri de libro vitae,</hi> to be blotted <note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> out of the boke of life: and ſaint Paule <hi rend="roman">Anathema eſſe a Chriſto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Roma. ix.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">pro fratribus,</hi> to be accurſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte for his brethren. And their prouiſion for theſe foure laſt thinges being on this wiſe layd for, &amp; circumſpectly made, God ſhall graunt them all, and ſende vnto them a quiet &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed death, and a moſt conforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and mercyfull iudgement, deliuering them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble paynes of hel, and reſtoring
<pb facs="tcp:12753:23"/> them to the eternall bliſſe and ioyes of heauen. All the reſt of <note place="margin">Shepe of the flocke of Chriſte.</note> Chriſtes familie or houſholde, whiche are not ſhepardes but ſhepe of his folde and paſture: You muſt here begin and make your prouiſion for theſe iiij. laſt thynges. Firſt by a diligent gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing eare, and harkening to the voices of your ſheperdes, &amp; by a circumſpecte and wyſe refuſall of all counterfeit and ſtraunge voyces. When the true ſhepe of Chriſte <hi rend="roman">non ſequuntur alienum,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioan. x.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">ſed fugiunt ab illo, quia non noue runt voces alienoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> do not folow a ſtraunge ſhepard, but flee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, for they know not the voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſtraungers. Neither will they be deceyued by the ſtraunge voyces of the Ary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <note place="margin">Aryans.</note> in deniyng the deitie of our Sauioure Chriſte: nor by the
<pb facs="tcp:12753:23"/> ſtraunge voices of the Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <note place="margin">Neſtorius Eutices.</note> and Eutichianes in denei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of Chriſtes humanitie: nor by the ſtraunge voyces of the Manichees in their deniall of <note place="margin">Manes.</note> the fre choiſe of man: nor yet by the ſtraunge voices of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagianes <note place="margin">Pelagius.</note> attributing to muche to the free will of man. When the trewe ſhepe of Chriſte will not be deceyued by the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyn voyce of Eunomius the <note place="margin">Eunomius</note> Solifidiane, nor by the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous voyce of Beringarius, <note place="margin">Beringari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> in hys denyall of Chriſtes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye Reall and bodelye preſence in the mooſte bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of the altare, nor yet by the euill ſkreakinge and moſte ſtraunge voyces of Martyn <note place="margin">Luther. Bucer. Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr.</note> Luther, Martyn Bucer, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr, Corolaſtadius,
<pb facs="tcp:12753:24"/> Zwynglius, Oecola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>padius &amp; <note place="margin">Zwinglius. Oecolam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>padius.</note> other, the very palebreakers of the vnitie of chriſtes church, the breders of al ſciſmes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the ſame, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blaſphemers of chriſtes ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerters of all good orders and conſtitutions, the reuiuers of olde cankered and ruſtie here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and now by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> newe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhed and ſet forth to the ſhew and therfore their bokes iuſtly condemned here in this realme by a late proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet forth by the kinge and Quenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties. Wherunto I do exhorte you to be obedient, &amp; to bringe in your bokes of hereſies, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the purport therof: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuche as the trewe ſhepe of Chriſte will geue no eare vnto their mooſte monſtrous and ſtraunge voyces: when theſe
<pb facs="tcp:12753:24"/> &amp; al other like voices which do diſwade from the antiquitie, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and vniuerſalitie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes church muſt nedes be moſt monſtrous and ſtraunge voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Therfore O ye Londoners and inhabitauntes of this cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <note place="margin">Londoners</note> Ceaſſe youre greate foly I beſech you, &amp; be you no longer <hi rend="roman">ſicut gens abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio &amp; ſine prudentia,</hi> as people withoute good counſell, and all foreſight what wil enſue &amp; folowe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: <hi rend="roman">Vtinam ſaperetis &amp; intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geretis, ac nouiſſima prouideretis</hi> Woulde God you woulde be wiſe, perceiue and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; make prouiſion for theſe. iiij. laſte thinges, by eſchewyng of all ſtraunge voices, and herke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge vnto the voyces of your ſheperdes, &amp; by a dyligente cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge of youre ſelues into ſome
<pb facs="tcp:12753:25"/> better remembraunce, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng how longe time they haue ſpent in calling vpon you, with how much patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce your ſlouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full retourne from your wicked errours and heriſies hathe bene borne withall at the handes of God, at the handes of our moſt noble king and oure moſte mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull lady and Quene, and alſo at the handes of your Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes and preachers among you. Wheras you beynge perſons ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced with many ſtraunge voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of theſe deceitfull Mayre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maides do dailie reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence this their moſt mercifull tolleration and gentilenes, with moſt cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and wycked ſpeakynges, blaſphemyng God, and reyſing vp falſe lyes and rumors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte oure mooſte gratious kynge and Quene. In ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:12753:25"/> that I for my part at this time occupiynge this place (of verye greate zeale and loue whyche I haue euer borne vnto you,) am forſed thus muche to ſaye vnto you: that excepte you geue better eare to the voyces of youre ſhepardes: excepte ye ſhortlye retourne frome youre wycked hereſyes into the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Chriſtes churche agayne: and excepte you become wyſe and vnderſtande, and ſhortlye amende thys youre ſmale re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde and mooſte euill prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on makynge for theſe foure laſt thinges: Doutles your euill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuynge and corrupte lyuynge ſhall brynge you vnto a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and lamentable deathe and endynge: and to receaue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at the handes of God, a ſtrayte and mooſte vpryghte
<pb facs="tcp:12753:26"/> iudgement, to your great loſſe of eternall ioye and bliſſe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge: and to the wynninge of the perpetuall tormentes &amp; paynes of hell.</p>
            <p>Ye gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and noble men whiche in lyuynge here in thys <note place="margin">Gentlemen and noble men.</note> worlde be very politike and ful of all maner of worldlie proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi rend="roman">Vtinam ſaperetis &amp; intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeretis ac nouiſſima prouidere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> Woulde God you woulde be wiſe, and vnderſtande, &amp; make prouiſion for theſe foure laſte thynges, that you maye finiſhe the race &amp; courſe of this ſhorte life with a quiet death, and fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallye to receaue at the handes of God a mercifull iudgement. into ioye and blyſſe, and not to ſuſteyne the tormentes of hell. The maner of this your proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion makinge muſte be, by the
<pb facs="tcp:12753:26"/> maintenaunce of Goddes glorie and honoure, by youre vprighte miniſtration of Iuſtice, &amp; by the authoritie committed vnto you of God, to defende the catholike fayth and religion of God, hys churche and moſte bleſſed ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and all the miniſters of the ſame, ſeruinge God in theyr byſhopriches, Cathedral chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, houſes of religion, vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, colleges or elles where. When otherwiſe doubtles your prouiſion made for theſe foure laſt thinges ſhall be all to ſhorte and after a wronge ſorte. O ye therfore that are <hi rend="roman">ſicut gens abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio et fine prudentia,</hi> as people voide of counſell, wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and all forſight: <hi rend="roman">vtinam ſaperetis</hi> Would God you would be wiſe and vnderſtande whether this your prouiſion by you and your
<pb facs="tcp:12753:27"/> aduyſe and counſell made here (as for an example) in this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral church of Paules, where of the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of. lviij. or. lx. prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, be nowe left by your proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but onely twelue prieſtes, called Peticanones, here daylie to ſerue God in the Queere: whether this your prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of Goddes glorie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure in all your doyng, may be called a prouyſion, or rather a ſubtraction or plaine diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame. O ye that are wandrynge here in thys worlde <hi rend="roman">ſicut gens abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio et ſiue prudentia,</hi> as people without counſell and voyde of wiſedom and all forſyghte: Is this a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the vpholding of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes catholike faith and religion here in this reaulme by nighte and daye prayer, by readynge,
<pb facs="tcp:12753:27"/> preachinge and teachyng, by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall almes geuinge and relei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of the poore membres of Chriſte, to ouerthrowe mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, colleges &amp; hoſpitalles, to ſpoile biſhopriches and their Cathedral churches, ſo craftely to cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe &amp; fleeſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſities by a couetous exchaungynge of theyr landes? Is this your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion? <hi rend="roman">O gens abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilio &amp; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne prudentia.</hi> O ye people voyde of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng &amp; fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight: <hi rend="roman">Vtina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaperetis.</hi> O woulde God you wold once beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e wiſe, to perceyue &amp; vnderſtande that excepte ye ſhortlie repent and do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce here in ſeaſon for your greate wyckednes, here to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, here to make ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore againe, doubtles your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for theſe. iiij. laſt thinges
<pb facs="tcp:12753:28"/> will be verye ſlender and ryght noughte worthe. When other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you ſhall be ſure here to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe your liues with a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and moſt miſerable death, and finally receiue at the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of God a fearfull and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: to the loſſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ioye and blyſſe: and to the winninge of the euerlaſting paynes and tormentes of hell. And here a litle further, &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more generally to ſpeake touching the prouiſion making for theſe foure laſte thinges af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuche ſorte, and as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paule hath already preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto vs in his Epiſtle to the Epheſians the .v. and .vi. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, as firſt: Suche among vs as be maryed and haue wiues, <note place="margin">Maried me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> let them prouide by a godly loue vnto their wyues: like as Saint
<pb facs="tcp:12753:28"/> Paule teacheth, ſaying: <hi rend="roman">Viri di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligite</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. v<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi rend="roman">vxores veſtras, ſicut chriſtus dilexit ſponſam ſuam eccleſiam, et ſemetipſum tradidit pro ea.</hi> Ye huſbandes, ſaieth ſainct Paule loue your wyues like as Chriſte loued his ſpouſe the church, and gaue him ſelfe for her. Ye mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <note place="margin">Maried women.</note> women and wyues, you muſte make youre prouiſion by your due obeyſaunce vnto your huſbandes. The Apoſtle Paule willing the ſame, ſaieth. <hi rend="roman">Mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. v.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">viris ſuis ſubditae ſint, ſicut do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino, quoniam vircaput eſt muli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eris, ſicut chriſtus caput eſt eccleſiae Sicut igitur eccleſia ſubiecta eſt chriſto, ita &amp; mulieres virisſuis in omnibus.</hi> Ye women, fayeth he, be you ſubiecte vnto youre huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes as vnto the Lorde. For the huſbande is the head of the woman, as Chriſte is the head
<pb facs="tcp:12753:29"/> of the churche. Therfore like as the church is ſubiect vnto chriſt, ſo let women be to their huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in all thinges. Suche as be fathers and haue children, you <note place="margin">Fathers.</note> muſt prouide by a godlie &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous education of your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi rend="roman">Et vos patres,</hi> ſaith ſainct Paule, <note place="margin">Epheſi. vi.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">nolite ad iracu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diam prouocare fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os veſtros: Sed educate illos in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplina et correctione domini.</hi> And ye O fathers, ſaith he, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke not your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to anger, but bringe them vp in the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our lord. And ye children, ye muſt make <note place="margin">Children.</note> your prouiſion by re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dryng your dewe obedience vnto youre pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, and by honourynge and reuerencing of them. For ſo S. Paule teacheth you ſayinge. <hi rend="roman">Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. vi.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">obedite pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus veſtris in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino: Hoc enim iuſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt. Honora</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12753:29"/> 
               <hi rend="roman">patre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuum, et matrem tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt bene ſit tibi et ſis longaeuus ſuper terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> O ye children, ſaith the apoſtle, obey your parentes in our lord: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is right. Honour thy father &amp; thy mother, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maieſt proſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, &amp; lyue long vpon the earth. And al ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be maiſters &amp; haue <note place="margin">Maiſters.</note> ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes you muſt prouide by a dyſcrete gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of youre ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, <hi rend="roman">remitte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes minas,</hi> not by ouermuche threatenyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi rend="roman">ſcientes ꝙ et illoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et veſter domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt in coelis, et ꝙ perſonaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptio no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt apud deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Knowing that both their maiſter &amp; yours is in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god. And ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes <note place="margin">Seruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes</note> muſt make their proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by doyng their faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice &amp; obedience vnto their lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; maiſters. <hi rend="roman">Serui obedite do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis veſtris cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> timore et tremore</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12753:30"/> 
               <hi rend="roman">in ſimplicitate cordis veſtri, ſicut chriſto, non ad oculum ſeruientes quaſi hominibꝰ place<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſed vt ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ui chriſti facientes voluntate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>animo.</hi> O ye ſeruauntes, ſaieth Paule, obey your maiſters with feare &amp; trembling in the ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your hart, as it were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, not doyng ſeruice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eye, as they do whiche go about to pleaſe men, but as the ſeruauntes of Chriſt, doyng the wyll of God, euen from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye harte. So that all kynde of men for the time of their abode here in this worlde, muſte here make their prouiſion for theſe foure laſt thinges, whether they be maried or vnmaried, wife or ſyngle woman, parentes or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, maiſters or ſeruauntes, ſuperiours or inferiours, magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
<pb facs="tcp:12753:30"/> beari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g rule, or ſubiectes being ruled, whether they be of the clergy or of the laitie: Euery man muſt here prouide, by a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpecte and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t walke in their vocations for the loue, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure and frendſhip of God, by obſeruation of his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, Chriſt himſelfe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge the ſame, and ſayinge: <hi rend="roman">Si praecepta mea ſeruauerits, manebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. xv.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">in dilectione mea.</hi> If you wyll kepe my preceptes, you ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in my loue, and haue my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure and frendſhippe. Whoſe loue and frendſhippe at the laſt houre of deathe, ſhall ſtande vs in better ſtede then all the riches and lordſhyppes of the worlde: When at that houre, thoughe all thy frendes, kinneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes &amp; acquaintaunce ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:12753:31"/> come with millions of golde, or yet by force of armes, they maye not at that dreadful griſely and laſt houre, do thee anye helpe or comforte: When other helpe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge or ſuccoure at that tyme thou ſhalt haue none, but onely at the handes of God. Let vs therfore in all the meane ſpace of this preſent life ſo dread and feare God, ſo imbrace and loue him, and ſo honoure and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe hym, that we at the laſte houre maye haue his fauoure &amp; fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip. <hi rend="roman">Et ſi deus pro nobis quis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Roma. viij.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">contra nos?</hi> And yf god be on our ſide, who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be againſt vs? And then we ſhall be ſure to haue at the finiſhing and knitting vp of this life a verie quiet and a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful death: to receaue at the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of God a very merciful and moſte confortable iudgemente,
<pb facs="tcp:12753:31"/> therby to auoyde and eſcape the tormentes of Hell: and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite the ioyes of heauen. To the whiche he bring vs all that hath ſo derelie bought it for vs, by the effuſion of hys moſt precious blood. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; the holy ghoſte be al praiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> honor, &amp; glory for now and euermore.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12753:32"/>
            <p rend="italic">Imprinted at London by Robert Caly, within the precinct of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued houſe of the Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rs, nowe conuerted to an hoſpital, called Chriſtes hoſpitall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <closer rend="italic">
               <dateline>
                  <date>The .xx. day of Auguſt. M.D.L.V.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12753:32"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
